<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaracio[n] made at Poules Crosse in the cytye of London the fourth Sonday of Aduent by Alexander Seyton and Mayster Willyam Tolwyn, persone of S. Anthonynes in the sayd cytye of London, the yere of our Lord God M.D.XLJ.</title>
            <author>Seton, Alexander, d. 1542.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1542</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22249.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2331</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23278122</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23278122</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26498</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26498)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1803:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaracio[n] made at Poules Crosse in the cytye of London the fourth Sonday of Aduent by Alexander Seyton and Mayster Willyam Tolwyn, persone of S. Anthonynes in the sayd cytye of London, the yere of our Lord God M.D.XLJ.</title>
                  <author>Seton, Alexander, d. 1542.</author>
                  <author>Tolwyn, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Newly corrected &amp; ame[n]ded.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted at London in Saynt Sepulchres paryshe in the Olde Bayly by Rychard Lant,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1542?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26498:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26498:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>pictured border surrounding title page</figDesc>
                  <p>The decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made at Poules Croſſe in the Cytye of London / the fourth ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day of Aduent / by Alex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ander Seyton / and mayſter Willyam Tolwyn / per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone of S. Anthonynes in the ſayd cytye of London. the yere of our lord god M.D.XLI. Newly corrected &amp; ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="recantation_speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:26498:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26498:2"/>
            <head>¶ The declaration of Alexander Seyton.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD people / </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ſo it is / that vpon ſonday / the .xiiii. day of Nouember laſt paſt / I Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Seyton a Scottyſſhe man borne hauynge ben here to fore greatly ſuſpected / noted and infa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med of hereſy / and erronious opinions / and for the ſame / conuentyd before di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe Eccleſiaſticall iudges of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme / made within the paryſſhe churche of ſaynt Anthonynes (within the cytye and dioceſe of London) a ſermon in the mornynge of the ſayd ſondaye / before a great multitude / without any lycence of my Lorde byſhop of London / or any his offycers and contrary to theyr myndes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement / takyng for the ground of my ſermon the epyſtle of that day / ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of the fyrſt chapiter wrytten to the Philippians I nothing ſpekyng in that mornynge ſermon / eyther of Fre wyll / or choyſe of man with his reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liacyon / or iuſtificacyon / nether yet els of good workes or meryt / or value there of / Albeit I had good and iuſt occaſyon ſo to do / by reaſon of the ſayde Epyſtle. And moreouer that ſermon done / I came immediatly hyther to the ſermon made in this place / by a well lerned man and
<pb facs="tcp:26498:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>doctour of diuinite / in the vniuerſyte of Oxforth) and herd all the ſame / well no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng &amp; markyng his proces made vpon the ſeyd epiſtle / eſpecially touching Fre wyll or choyce of man / with his reconſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or iuſtification / &amp; alſo the prayſe of good workes / &amp; the meryttes &amp; value therof / than &amp; there openly declared / &amp; I was in dede in my mynde not right well contented with the ſeyd ſermon &amp; gretly offended with the ſame. For as much as touchyng Fre wyll or Choyſe &amp; iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation / or reconſylyation of man to god me thought as than the ſeyd precher ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to moch vnto man / &amp; dyd withdraw to moch from gods grace and touchyng good workes &amp; the meryt &amp; value therof As than me thought he dyd ouer moche value &amp; eſteme the ſame / &amp; beyng ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded / I the ſame day at after none within the ſayd church of ſaynt Antonyues be fore a gret multytude then &amp; there aſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled (without any lycens of my ſeid lord of London or any his offycers / &amp; contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to their myndes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes / yea &amp; without any ſhewing of any other lycens at all / of a ſet purpoſe &amp; to the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent the people ther aſſembled ſhuld not agree to the mynde &amp; declaracyon of the ſeyd precher / but vtterly diſſent / vary / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26498:3"/>clerely dyſagree from all the ſame) dyd make an other ſermon directed contrary in poyntes and artycles afore ſayd / vnto the ſermon of the ſeyd precher / the peple takyng occaſion there by to be in diſcord varyete &amp; diuerſite of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s amongeſt them ſelues / and there by not vnlyke to fall into further in conuenyens and buſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. Wherfore now I am right heuy / ſory / and greatly repentaunt / truſtynge in the mercy of God / to vſe here after a more modeſty diſcretion and temperans in my prechyng / and to auoyd ſuch raſh and haſty paſſyons and ſodayne affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / and only to cleue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the trouth and Catholyke determyna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyons of our holy mother the Church.</p>
            <p>☞ And more ouer ye ſhall vnderſtand good people / that as I was denounced detected and preſented / ſo alſo I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe it is euidently proued agaynſt me by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycient wytneſſe brought in there vpon / that in my ſayd ſecond ſermon than and there made at after none / I dyd contrary to good doctryne &amp; lernyng / vtter / prech / and declare amongeſt diuerſe other thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges .ii. thynges chefely / that were very erronyouſe / that is to wyt / that a man hath no lybertye or Frewyll at all to do my thynge that is vertuous and good
<pb facs="tcp:26498:4"/>and alſo that good workes dyd nothing at all helpe or were merytorious towar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des our ſaluacyon or iuſtificacion. And all be it my lord byſhop of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / iuſtly might for the ſame myne offences ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted within his iuriſdiction / haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled me / accordyng to the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal lawes of this Realme to abiure &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo might haue extremly punyſhed me for the ſame offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces / as in ſuch caſes here to fore hath ben a cuſtomed / yet ſuch is his charyte / gentylnes / &amp; goodnes towardes me / deſyryng only my reformacyon and amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with your ſatiſfaccion / that he for certayne cauſes and honeſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracions hym mouynge / haue ben and is contented with this onely pen aunce / (that is to ſay) That I make here this open declaracyon vnto you of my ſayde offences / &amp; that I do not here after prech or teach any ſuch thyng agayne / or any other thynge that ſhalbe agaynſt the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke fayth of our holy mother the church / but as moch as can lye in my po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer / to mayntayne / defend and auaunce the ſayde fayth and vtterly to deteſt and forſake all and all maner of hereſyes / er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rours &amp; noughty opynions with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers / mayntayners / defenders / or abbeters of them / or any of them / du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge
<pb facs="tcp:26498:4"/>my lyfe / which now I ſo promyſe and declare alſo vnto you / that I wyll do effectually. And for both your better vnderſtandyng / and alſo for myne owne declaracyon here in / and to the entent ye may knowe / that myne opinion is euen as the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is of the catholyke church and no otherwyſe. He ſhall vnderſtand that I do verely beleue and playnly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe / that a Chriſten man not deſtytute of gods grace hath lyberte / Frewyl and choyſe to do good / and alſo of hym ſelfe without Gods grace / hath lybertye to conſent to euyll / &amp; to do it in dede. Item that all thynges good and bad / are not to be aſcribed vnto a fynall deſtynye / pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſtinacyon / or foreknowledge of God / as the very cauſe thereof / ne yet to an ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolute or preſtyſe neceſſyte or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pulcyon that can not be auoyded / which in tymes paſt hath ben a lewd opynion / &amp; a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable hereſy holden of many. Item that thynges which be euyll / are to be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to our ſelfes / who wyllyngly &amp; wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynglye do conſent and agre vnto them. where aſſyſted with gods grace / beynge euer redy at hand we myght ſufficiently haue auoyded and made reſyſtence vnto them / yf we had wolde. Item that ſuch good workes as we do with the helpe of
<pb facs="tcp:26498:5"/>gods grace are by ſcripture truely called our good workes / as wrought by vs by the ſtrength of Gods grace and concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of our frewyll. And al be it we not only of humylyte / but alſo for confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the trouth / do aſcrybe them to god as by ryches of whoſe mercy we haue both grace &amp; frewyll / wherewith to worke yet neuertheleſſe god to ſet forth the trouth of excellence of the lyberty of our frewyl wroughte by hym in Chriſt / by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are deliuered calleth in his ſcripture. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo truly thoſe good works done by good men / theyr workes as truely done by them made able and ſtrengthned by god ſo to do &amp; therfore ſuch fantaſys as hath ben ſpred abrode / &amp; entred into rude me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eares as though god ſhuld worke in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the workes to be only Goddes / and man only an inſtrument to worke by / or a veſſell to worke in / is pernycyous dete<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtable &amp; to be abhorred / for ſuche places of ſcripture as ſpeke of gods workynge in vs are to be vnderſtanded as they may agre with the reſt of ſcrypture / wherein be innumerable places to declare / that god maketh his ſeruauntes in Chriſt ſo rych as they may by the plenty &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth there of / be good trees and brynge forth frute &amp; worke. And as Chriſt ſayd / Qui
<pb facs="tcp:26498:5"/>credit in me / opera que ego facio / faciet et maiora horum faciet. which ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtyn wrytynge on the ſame place very fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be ſpoken of a ſynner in his iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyon. And moreouer I do lykewyſe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue and confeſſe / that the good workes of a Chryſten man be by gods wyll / or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derynge them to be done / and his accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon merytorious / &amp; a meane or helping towards remiſſion of our ſynnes &amp; vnto our ſaluacynu. yea further I ſay and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue that all though our ſauyour and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demer Ieſus Chriſt ſent by God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fulfyll his wyll / hath accordyng vnto the ſame by his lyfe and paſſyon in erth appeſed the wroth of god towar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des man ſufficientlye and purchaſed for man great fauor and fredom / wherby he may be able to pleaſe God obtayne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſion of ſynnes / and do ſuch workes as God of his goodneſſe wyll rewarde with eternal lyfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet we muſt know and vnderſtande that accordynge to the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge of Chriſt declaryng the word of God vnto vs / all thoſe ſhal by the mene of Chriſt only be deliuered from goddes anger that come to Chriſt and in fayth both profeſſe his trouthe / receyuynge the Sacrament of Baptyme / and alſo worketh ſuche good workes to fulfyll
<pb facs="tcp:26498:6"/>gods wyll as tyme &amp; occaſyon doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to worke / for in theſe only / god is pleaſed / for Chriſt as ſcripture ſayth / &amp; to theſe only is promyſed euerlaſtyng lyfe / and therfore ſuch vayne opynions as hath entred percaſe into the hedes of ſome ignorant people in the eſtymacion of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s good workes that the ſame may be accompted no maner of helpe to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon / or remyſſion of ſynnes / leſt therby we ſhuld make .ii. menes or .ii. ſauyours where as in dede ſcriptur ſpeketh but of one meane and ſauyour. This fonde feare I ſaye is to be remoued and taken away by knowledge of trouth / which te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth / that by workes of penaunce we come to Chriſt / when we beyng preuen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by god and called are by the fyre of charyte which god kyndleth in vs / ſuch as come at his callynge / &amp; beleue in him ioyned in Chriſtes myſtycall body / and made one with hym / and ſo by hys mene he beynge the only hed / we begyn here a heuenly lyfe / and ſhall fynally enioye it in him our only ſauyour Ieſu Chriſt / in whom we here worke the wyll of god / &amp; therfore our workes be not another me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / or another ſanyour / but wrought in Chriſt by the grace purchaſed of god by Chriſt and by him requyred of vs / not as
<pb facs="tcp:26498:6"/>any other ſtraunge thyng or ſeed to ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ply any imperfection in him which were blaſphemye and madnes to be thoughte or ſayd / but becauſe it is the wyll of god who hath for our profyte ordeyned the regeneracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man / in this wyſe / which can not be but the beſt without diſcuſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and becauſe it is / his wyll is the beſt &amp; ſo to be folowed and obſerued of all that haue hope in their calling / to enioye god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des promyſſes made only to thoſe that fulfyll his wyll / which my ſaynges and opinyons in theſe poyntes eſpecyall I do proteſte euen from the botom of my hert / that I do beleue they are true. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as now I haue declared them vnto you and that alſo in all my ſermons and tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynges here after I wyll and entend af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the ſame ſort to declare &amp; vtter them vnto the people and none otherwyſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>¶ Ita eſt Alexander Seyton manu propria.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="recantation_speech">
            <head>¶ Here begynneth the declaracyon made the fourth ſonday in Aduent / the yere of our lorde god a thouſand v. hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth. xli by maſter Wyllyam Tolwyn / perſon of ſaynt Anthoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the cytye of London.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:26498:7"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>GOOD people / </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ſo it is / that I Wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyam Tolwyn / maiſter of Arte / and perſon of ſaint Anthonynes within this Tyte and Dyoceſe of London / haue ben laufully denounced / detected &amp; preſented to my Lorde byſſhop of London / that I haue ben and am a man vehemently ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected / noted and enfamed of hereſy and erronyous / heretycall &amp; ſedicyouſe opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyons agaynſt the Catholyke fayth of our holy mother the churche / and alſo a gret fauourer / defender / maynteynour &amp; receptour of heretykes / accuſtomed alſo to haue in my cuſtody / bokes of hereſy / &amp; other vnlauful workes forbydden by the kynges maieſties proclamations &amp; ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunces / and alſo contrary to the decree and inhthytion of myne Ordynary. And moreouer that I haue not a cuſtomed to obſerue &amp; kepe the laudable ceremonyes / rytes &amp; cuſtomes of this catholyke chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Englande / comenly obſerued and kepte by other. that is to ſay / neither in goyng of Proceſſyon vpon ſaturdays at Euynſonge / nor in the vſage and maner of makyng of holy water and holy bred / nor in makyng my confeſſyon or ſayeng of Maſſe / Matens or Euynſonge / as I ſhuld and ought to haue done.: Whiche denunciation / detectyon &amp; preſentation
<pb facs="tcp:26498:7"/>hath ben partly by my nowne confeſſion and partly by ſufficient wytnes &amp; record in that behalfe ſuffyciently proued.</p>
            <p>And albeit for myne offence in ſo doyng I knowledge to haue deſerued no ſmall punyſhment. yet I haue found ſuch cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytable goodnes and mercy in my Lorde byſſhop of London / vpon my ſubmiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſute vnto him / that vpon only this declaration here made of my offeus vnto you / with promyſe that I wyll endeuer my ſelfe to the beſt of my power to lyue as a Catholyke man ought and ſhuld do hereafter: And that I doo not hereafter preach or teach any Hereſyes / Errours or noughtye opinyons / contrary and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Catholyke fayth of our holy mother the Church / but as moch as can lye in my power to mayntayne / defende and auaunce the ſayde Catholyke fayth and vtterly to deteſt / abhorre and auoyd all and all maner of Hereſyes / Errours and noughty opinyons / with the fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers / mayntaynours / defendours or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beters of them or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> durynge my lyfe / his lorſhyp is content to reſpyt the reſt of my penaunce / and vpon my good deſeruynge and doyng accordyng to my ſeyd promyſe to forgyue all togyther / be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſechyng therfore you that be my fryndes
<pb facs="tcp:26498:8"/>to gyue hym moſt herty thankes for the ſame / &amp; to take example by me to auoyd the lyke daunger.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Here after foloweth the names of the bokes / whiche the ſayd perſon of ſ. Anthonines was detected and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>GOod people / </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>theſe bokes contayned here in this bagge or ſachel are er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronyous / hereticall and noughty bokes and were remaynyng and founde in my houſe and cuſtody what tyme I was de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounced / and detected to my Lorde byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of London / &amp; the names of the ſayd bokes are theſe / A boke of Frythes / a boke called Thorpe and Olde caſtell / the Olde god and the New / Rydleys comen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taryes vpon ſaynt Poule to the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / Venatorious vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Timothe / Swyn glyus of gods prouydence / Cathecyſme of Melancton / the Cathecyſme of Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus / the cathecyſme of Pacymonta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus / the cathecyſme of Sarcerius / Weſt more vpon the concylyacion of fathers / the boke of the counterfayt byſſhop / the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon in Englyſh with the Apology Poſtylles vpon the Epiſtels &amp; goſpels / a boke of prayer made by Luther / the Dore of holy ſcrypture / the Poſtelles of Coruynus / two old wrytten bokes / the
<pb facs="tcp:26498:8"/>one for ſcolers / and thother taken out of Frythes bokes. In which bokes are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned many ſundry errours and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous / deteſtable / and abhominable hereſyes / not onely agaynſt the bleſſed ſacrament of thaulter with other ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of Chryſtes church / but alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the fre wyll of man / makyng god thautor of ſyn / And moreouer agaynſt good workes / ſpecially faſtyng / prayer / almys dede / agaynſt auriculer confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt the vow of chaſtyte / and for the maryage of preeſtes / agaynſt the rytes &amp; ceremonyes of the churche / comparyng the maner of weddyng / and maryeng of Vyrgens / vnto the beſtyall facyon of a ſawte bytch. Agaynſt mens lawes &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicyons / agaynſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyon or houſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng at Eſter &amp; vnder one kynd / agaynſt inuocations of ſayntes / agaynſt Maſſe Matens &amp; Euynſonge / agaynſt the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of an Oth before a iudge / &amp; fynally to haue althing come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the people</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>¶ It a eſt Wilhelmus Tolwyn manu propria.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in ſaynt Sepulchres paryſſhe / in the Olde Bayly / by Rychard Lant.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26498:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
